Guide to the Danny M. Samuels Photographs Collection MS 1008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Danny M. Samuels Photographs Collection
1977-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Samuels, Danny
MS 1008
2 Linear Feet 1 box + 1 oversize box
0.391 Gigabytes MS1008aip_001
Photographs and supporting information from two Photography series 21 Little Buildings and Photographing Italy.
Biographical / Historical
Danny Marc Samuels, FAIA, is a Professor in Practice of Architecture and the Co-director of Construct. After apprenticing with Guillermo Jullian de la Fuente in Paris and Venice, he founded, with partners John J. Casbarian and Robert H. Timme, the design firm, Taft Architects, in 1973. The work of this Houston-based office has received over 60 major design awards, and has appeared in over 200 articles in books and journals worldwide. Samuels, with his partners, has lectured at over 100 professional and educational forums, nationally and internationally. Together they are recipients of the Houston AIA Educator Award and the Houston AIA Firm Award. Samuels is a Fellow of the American Academy in Rome, and in 1991 was elected to the College of Fellows of the American Institute of Architects.
Samuels' work through the Rice Building Workshop with Associate Director Nonya Grenader, and now through Construct with Co-director Andrew Colopy has resulted in a stream of realized projects: over the past twenty-five years, more than seven hundred students have designed and built projects at various scales in the community -- from exhibit venues in Houston museums to affordable housing at Project Row Houses in Houston's Third Ward. The Workshop received the 2004 NCARB Prize for the "Integration of Practice and Education" from the National Council of Registration Boards and the "Collaborative Practice Award" in 2005 from the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture. In 2015/16, the RBW collaboration with Project Row Houses was the subject of exhibitions at Harvard GSD, AIA NY, and the Cooper Hewitt Museum, as well as the book Core Houses.
Profile taken from https://arch.rice.edu/people/faculty/danny-samuels
Content Description
Photographs from the "Little Buildings Series," photographs from the "Italian Series," atlas of Italy with the routes Samuels took highlighted in yellow, his notes on the Little Buildings photographs, articles, Tony Cronin's draft essays, catalog from The Anthony G. Cronin Memorial Collection at MFAH, and a flashdrive with enhanced images of all photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated by Danny M. Samuels in 2022.
Arrangement
The materials in the collection are arranged in two series: Series I: Documents and Series II: Photographs and Ephemera.
Index Terms
Subjects
Photography
Document Types
photographs
- Series I. Documents
  - 21 Little Buildings background information (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographing Italy background information (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anthony G. Cronin Memorial Collection background information and catalog (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II. Photographs and Ephemera
  - Sub-series A. 21 Little Buildings, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Photographs of buildings taken by Danny Samuels across the southern United States in 1976-1979. "A study of the morphology of storefronts."
    - Bob Early (Hays) Gro., Paragould, Arkansas
    - Foreign Car Parts, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1977-10
    - Shady Lady, Houston, Texas, 1978-03
    - B&J Machinery, Sealy, Texas, 1977-09
    - Storefront, TX 35, Texas, 1978-03
    - Emmett Seafood, Houston, Texas, 1978-03
    - Fine Carpentry Cabinets, Texas, 1979-03
    - Geo. Seiman & Co., Gen'l Mdse., Leesville, Louisiana, 1978-07
    - W.M. Ryza, near Fayetteville, Texas, 1977-10
    - Joe's Grocery Market, Ferriday, Louisiana, 1978-03
    - Andy's Garage, Pasadena, Texas, 1979-05
    - Warrenton Grocery, Warrenton, Texas, 1978-03
    - Bill's Lounge, Houston, Texas, 1978-06
    - Murry Chapel, near Longstreet, Louisiana, 1978-07
    - E.C. Minssen General Merchandise, Willow Springs, Texas, 1977-07
    - Pilgrim Rest Baptist Church, near Waco, Texas, 1979-04
    - Waco Metal Mfg. Co., Waco, Texas, 1978-07
    - Apartment building. Houston, Texas, 1977-06
    - Rico's Triangle Cafe, Houston, Texas, 1978-11
    - W.B. Donald Chevrolet Co., Jennings, Louisiana, 1978-03
  - Sub-series B. Photography Italy (Box 2)
    Photographs of historic works of architecture in color in their contemporary contexts in Italy.
    - Pantheon, Roma, December 1985
    - palazzo di Mercato Vecchio, Verona, May 1987
    - Duomo, Ferrara, May 1987
    - Duomo, Orvieto, September 1986
    - S. Lorenzo de Arari (Interior), Orvieto, September 1986
    - Cupola di Santa Maria del Fiore, Firenze, September 1986
    - Tempio Maletestiana, Rimini, May 1987
    - S. Andrea, Mantova, September 1986
    - Cortile, Palazzo Ducale, Urbino, May 1987
    - Tempietto di S. Pietro in Montorio, Roma, December 1985
    - Santa Maria in Trivio, Roma, January 1986
    - Ss. Martina e Luca, Roma, January 1986
    - S. Ivo della Sapienza, Roma, January 1986
    - S. Carlino all Quatro Fontane, Roma, January 1986
    - Cappella S. Luigi, Corteranzo (Torino), October 1987
    - Santuario del Vallinotto (Interior), Carignano (Torino), September 1987
    - Corte Gonzahesca, Spinosa (Mantova), May 1987
    - Chiesa, Sabbionetta, October 1987
    - Chiesa, Sabbionetta, May 1987
    - Chiesa di Santa Maria Assunta, Sabbionatta, May 1987
    - Chiesa, Fanzolo (near Rovigo), September 1986
    - Chiesa Annunciazione Della Beata Vergine Maria, Boccadiganda (Mantova), October 1987
    - Chiesa, Viadana (Mantova), May 1989
    - Chiesa, Casatico, October 1987
    - Cappella, Santena (Torino), September 1986
    - Chiesa (+ garage), S. Lorenzo (Mantova), October 1987
    - Cappeletta, S. Gaudenzio (Pavia), May 1987
    - Cappeletta B.V. di Carravaggio, Pieve S. Giacomo (Cremona), October 1987
    - Cappelletta, Pieve del Cairo (Milano), June 1989
    - Oratorio Ca' Moro, Belvedere (Bassano del Grappa), May 1987
    - Chiesa, Rivarolo d. Re, October 1987
    - Chiesa, Sesta Cremonese (Cremona), May 1989
    - Piazza Giuseppe Finzi, Canicossa (Mantova), May 1987
    - Corte Castiglioni (library), Casatico (Mantova), May 1987
    - Corte Castiglioni (courtyard), Casatico (Mantova), May 1987
    - Corte Castiglioni (courtyard), Casatico (Mantova), May 1987
    - Cascina Colombarone (ext), S. Daniele Po (Cremona), May 1987
    - Cascina Colombarone (courtyard), S. Daniele Po (Cremona), May 1987
    - Cascina Castello, Stagno Lombardo (Cremona), September 1987
    - Kiln, Prato, September 1986
    - Bureau de Vincennes ou du Trone, Paris, January 1987
  - Enhanced photographs USB drive (Box 2)
  - Touring Club Italiano road map of Italy with annotations (Box 2)